Okay. Um so at this point in the song of
my spiritual life uh I
guarant if if the Buddha could see us
right that's the what what's the name of
that meditation?
Come on. Kelly knows cuz she got
that cheshure cat
smile. The
andine international bathroom
meditation. Okay. Right. Uh if if the
Buddha could can see us now and is
watching us in class and and then are in
the garden also. Okay. There are two
great streams of wisdom that come to us.
Two great streams of wisdom that you
need to practice diamond ray. Okay. And
I guess that's the most
important idea this time is that there's
two streams of lam rim staircase people
uh coming to us and uh one is our okay
and uh he's the great master of
emptiness. He wrote a book called
wisdom. He likes to write poetry. He
likes to make it very
short, but still it's very clear, but it
has like a thousand meanings. It's
extremely difficult to
translate. Sonappa wrote
about 4,000 pages to explain a few
verses, you know, and uh we're we're
working through those explanations. we
finished about uh 2 and a half thousand
pages. So that's the main thing I'm
working on and I waited 50 years to do
it because I wanted to be
ready. So
uh so we'll be we'll be we'll be going
to that. We'll be teaching that. I think
we're going to teach some of that
at DSU. Uh okay. And
uh uh those are great seed planters in
your mind to study those books. I wanted
to talk at this point about the goodn
night book club. Okay.
Uh
so in the
last I don't know in the last two or
three years
uh I don't know how it started. Oh, a
friend of mine, Will Duncan, who was one
of the first students here, uh, he has a
small retreat center. He has a farm. He
has a farm that makes the same amount of
money as my
cafe. And, uh, I'm not sure who's ahead.
Uh, he makes lavender. He plants big
farm for lavender and about two hours
from Rimrod. And uh so anyway, I heard
that on the
weekend he does uh special small
retreats like for three people, four
people and then uh I heard this a long
time ago. He takes away their cell
phone, he takes away their
computer and then just to be safe, he
turns off the internet in the house and
you can't get online even you want to
get online. So, uh, you know, I thought
it was a little bit too extreme, you
know. I thought I can't do that. I
thought it was sweet and and Will is
sweet. He's like that. I thought that's
sweet, you know. That's nice. Not
something I could ever do.
I tried it. you know some my I think my
doctor said you should try sleeping uh
more hours
and uh
our parents always told us you know I
don't know about you my school teachers
when I was 12 years old when I was eight
years old they used to say you should
sleep for eight hours every night you
know so I grew up I don't know in your
country do they tell people that in
Singapore I don't know it's the same
useless advice
Uh they say you should sleep for eight
hours, you know, then you get to
be when you get to high school,
you know, and then in we were talking
about it in Dunang in my
experience in New York corporate life,
uh if you want if you're serious, you
know, if you really want to climb the
corporate ladder, and I did. I spent 19
years at the top of the corporate
ladder. You have to show you're serious.
Okay, you two Singaporeans, you you have
to
overwork. You have to not sleep. Uh you
know, otherwise no one takes you
seriously. And and and then when you get
there in the
morning, you have to brag about it. You
know, somebody will say, "I only slept
six hours." You say, "I only slept five
hours." And then somebody else says, "I
didn't sleep at all." And
you're then you think they're serious.
You think they're really serious. I
remember in Tokyo. I was in Tokyo and uh
I hate to say it, but me and all my
friends went to a nightclub, not to
drink, just to dance. And we we danced
all night. And uh then we they stopped
music. We said, "What's going on?" and
the dawn comes coming up. And uh so we
went
outside and we saw this u
zombie is a businessman with this
briefcase and a suit and he's
like, you know, and they're getting on
the subway. I'm like, what's going on?
They're supposed to get off the subway.
No, no, no. They're going home. You
know, the sun came up. They can go home
now. you know, so it it means you're a
tough guy or or you're a serious
worker. So anyway, I I decided I would
try to sleep I don't know why, but I
decided to try to sleep eight hours. Oh,
it was because of COVID. So during So I
never had a television. I never watched
movies. Never ever uh in my whole life
since I was since I went to university.
Since I was 16, I never had a
television and um I never looked at
movies online and stuff like that. Then
during co
uh I couldn't travel and I and I got
bored and I started watching first I
watch uh what do you call football games
then I start to watch movies then I sign
up for Amazon Netflix then fo then
Disney you know and then I start
watching war movies then I start
watching dirty movies then I and then 2
o'clock in the morning I'm waking waking
up to watch another movie and then I I
was like this is not good for the
teacher you know like I should I
shouldn't be doing this and uh you know
I tried to stop it was difficult it was
really difficult to stop and I was
really addicted what was the final
problem Korea's soap
operas they're really
cool uh the emperor's affection did you
see
Come
[Music]
on. She and her brother are the crown
prince and crown
princess in Korea in ancient times. He
gets killed as a
child. Then the auntie raises up the
girl as the prince. Tells everybody the
prince didn't die. Then up until she's
like 30, she has to pretend to be the
prince. which gets to into some
interesting things.
Okay. With her
boyfriend anyway, you're not going to
watch it.
Um, so I I just couldn't control myself.
And then I found I then we, you know,
me, Lindsay, other people, we made the
goodn night book club. And this is how
it works. Uh, you
agree to You got that bag?
Yeah. And I'm not trying to sell
anything, okay? If you if you don't have
if you want, I'll give it to you, okay?
Uh I gave away about a couple hundred
already. I lost a lot of money. Uh but
um so this carry bag that Rosa
designed, it's part of the luxury
business. She produces it in China.
Inside there's a val. we call
val zipper for your computer and your
phone and then at night uh I have a rule
at 10:00 I put the computer in here I
zip it and I put my phone with it and uh
if I'm traveling I put the
hotel TV controller in it and uh if my
wife's with me I put it on next to her
on this on on the floor me of the her
side of the bed. It's very hard to
sneak. It's very hard to get it away
from her even when she's asleep. She
go I tried where you're laughing. I I I
did it a few times successfully, but
then she caught me and and then I I just
realized I can't control myself. And uh
and so so I put Rosa designed a lock.
There's a time lap. Okay. There's a time
lapse on the zipper. Yeah. And it's it's
awesome. You You can't get it open. I
mean, I I actually took a knife and I
was like, "Okay, I'm gonna cut it open."
And then I'm like, "What are you doing?
You're supposed to be the
teacher." So, anyway, you set it for 10
p.m. And then, uh, you set it for 6:00
a.m. And And I never got up early. John
Brady gets up
early. I can't do it. I He gets up at 4
and
meditates, you know, and
everyone says to me, "Oh, G Michael, you
probably get up at 3. You know, if John
gets up at 4, you probably get up at 3."
And I don't want to tell him I get up at
8:30 or something. And so, but I tried.
I got up at 6:00 and it worked because I
didn't have my computer. I didn't have
my phone. It's actually nothing else to
do except sleep. And uh so 10:00 I I go
to bed. Then I started reading
um in the monastery in the gishi course
when I have trouble sleeping
uh I will read Majimika
uh middleway school
uh and then I'll fall asleep within 10
minutes or five I'll fall asleep on the
book and uh so I I've my whole life I
I've realized if you go to
believe with uh scripture in your mind
uh strange things happen and uh I think
DCI we're going to teach there's called
advanced level five it will come out
in
shaman in shaman we'll do the first
release in shaman in June and uh it will
include lucid dreaming lucid dreaming
means in my case I designed programs in
my sleep and AL5 that program was
designed in my sleep and uh and then
people tell me
uh that's weird Gisha I have you know
I'm tired enough when I go to bed I
don't need to be working during my sleep
but uh you you can work during your
sleep and when you wake up you feel
super fresh you feel totally relaxed and
it's like super sleep. You get work done
and you super sleep. It's called lucid
dreaming and it's part of the diamond
way
actually uh swapna yoga. Swapna yoga. So
anyway, we'll teach it in shaman. We'll
release it in
shaman and
I so the idea is you you get a paper
book at 10:00. You lock up your phone.
You lock up your
computer. By the way, don't try to put
it in a
drawer. You won't be able to do it. I'm
telling you. And I'm not an addicted
type of personality, you know, like I I
I never was addicted to movies or or
stuff. Um but it's not enough to put it
in a drawer. I can tell you that, you
know, 2
a.m. you're trying not to make noise,
you know, because your wife's over
there. Then there's this blue glow in
your face and she comes out and she sees
a ghost or something and you know so
anyway uh I found out for myself and I'm
not an addicted type of person. I don't
drink alcohol. I don't I never smoked. I
but I I
I can't stop myself. I I will use the
phone. I remember the night I tried to
start this new system and
um and I I woke up like 11 o'clock and I
said, "Oh my god, I got to where's my
phone?" And I couldn't find my phone. By
the way, you have to buy a cheap
uh uh alarm clock, battery alarm clock.
I buy I have one I carry with me. So
that's how I wake up. Then uh I wake up
and I'm looking for my phone, you know?
I'm like, and I'm having a panic attack.
And then I I'm like, what what did you
need to check? And I was like, I was
going to check. I had something
important. Does your fingernails grow
faster or your toenails grow faster? You
know, and I was going to look it up
online, you know, and then I'm like,
maybe you don't have to know that at
12:00, you know, maybe you could, if you
want to, maybe you could wait till
tomorrow to check about that. But then I
realized how addicted I am to stupid
information, useless information. You
know, it doesn't help anybody. You know,
they're still going to grow the same
speed, you know, and it doesn't matter
if I look it up, you know. So, anyway,
uh if you just put it in a drawer, you
won't be able to control yourself. You
you'll you'll be opening the drawer, you
know, checking the toenail thing. And uh
so I lock it up, you know, especially
when I travel. When I travel, Rob uh we
have an agreement. He takes it at 10:00.
He comes to my hotel room. He takes it
at 10:00 and then he brings it back at
6:00. And uh that's I haven't snuck into
his room yet. Uh I mean, it's a it's an
option, but but uh he'll probably wake
up.
Uh but I we'll talk more about it. We
you know I I've been teaching it
everywhere I go because what happened to
me was my productivity tripled. I I can
do three times more work and I send it
out every morning so people know people
know it's real, you know. Uh and I'm
transcending Narajjuna now. It's it's a
4,000page project and
um and because I get good sleep, my work
is unbelievable. The the work is
unbelievable. Much much more productive.
So you you feel like if I go to bed
early and I wake up early, if I sleep so
long, 8 hours, I can't get any work
done, you know, like I'm going to lose a
lot of work. But it doesn't work like
that. Uh if you sleep eight hours a
night, which I've never done in my whole
life except for the last two years since
I'm doing this, you sleep eight hours,
you wake up and then you work like uh
the work is high quality, very high
quality and very fast. And so I really
encourage you to try it. Why I'm talking
about
that? Because of Arya Gardina. Where did
he go?
That to me that's the best one to read.
See 10:00 you get a paper book and you
read uh you just read for five minutes
10 minutes okay read something deep read
something complex read something you
don't understand and then uh it puts
seeds in your mind and so I always read
Neaja at 10:00 at 10:00 I I I get my
Negajuna books I get my mixed nuts
translations because I you know you
can't understand anything and then uh I
read a couple pages and it puts me into
a deep sleep. Uh sometimes the book even
falls down you know
and but something happens to your mind
the seeds are planted in your mind.
Okay.
uh the great books of the diamond way
especially uh the two flows the two
rivers into the diamond way which one is
emptiness one is bodh's sata activity
uh they
are they they are not something you read
and you put it away when I read I read a
lot of science fiction for fun and I
read it once you know and then I I put
it away and my wife is she always for my
birthday she goes to the bookstore and
she says what's a good science fiction
book and they give her a science fiction
book you know and then she she she gives
it to me she wraps it up I open it up
then I I look at it I said yeah I read
that you know I read that when I was 12
you know my mom made a mistake she said
uh I'll sign you up for the science
fiction book club you can have as many
books as you want. And I finished one
every two days or something. And the
whole garage was full of science fiction
books. And and what I mean is modern
books, they're not worth reading again.
You say, you read them once, the same
guy got killed, the same person, you
know, then uh these ancient
books, you you can't understand them.
They are not entertaining, okay? Uh
they're not like a TV show and they're
hard and you're like, "This is not the
way I want to go to sleep, you know. I
want to go to sleep. I want I want the
hero to kiss the girl, you
know, you know, and then I fall asleep."
But if
you read a little bit of ancient book,
uh just before between start at 10:00,
right? So 10:00 you put your computer
away and then you get your ancient book.
Now everybody has one. You can't tell me
you don't have one. I know you got
Gibson's book. Uh then read it for a few
minutes. Uh and you you'll get tired and
you sleep. Okay? Sleep for eight hours.
And what happens during the eight hours
is those great ideas cook in your mind.
Those books you can read a hundred times
and you won't understand. you you won't
go to the bottom. It takes a hundred it
takes several hundred times to read it.
So as you fall
asleep, you don't even have to do it in
order. Just open it. Okay? In according
to Diamond
Way. It's a message. Okay? It's a
message and it's fun. You're like,
"What's the message today?" You know,
and you go this and it says copyright
No, I'm
kidding. But you see if there's some
message see if there's some message for
you. Okay? And it's it's a wonderful
practice. Okay? And so what I mean is
your relationship to
nagana. It's not a normal relationship.
You don't read his book, put it away,
get a degree, and you're done with it.
You It's something you have to keep
reading your whole life. Okay. And and
it will affect you after you die. It's
it's a book that will affect you after
you die. Okay. So anyway, there's two
streams of books like that. One is
Neggina. And by the way, he saved he had
a book saving project. I think John
Brady might be Nearuna's reincarnation.
Uh Shenzang
uh around
6:45 something like that. He walked to
India for 17 years. He visited
Nearajin's
database. You know, Nearjuna had a
special library. He collected all the
books and Shenzang went there and saw
it. And just like John Brady, Nearina
saved a lot of books. Nega talked the
dragons out of a lot of books and that's
why they show him. Those are supposed to
be dragons over his head and that's why
his name is Nagajuna. Nag Naga Arjuna,
the king of the the lord of the dragons.
Okay.
Long. Okay. There's another dragon, but
I'm not supposed to talk about it yet.
Right.
[Music]
Uh oh, there's a group of people who uh
there's an old story that
uh so Kappa was teaching Diamond Way and
then he uh he
said he was at Gandan this he he was one
of the great early monasteries that he
founded.
And then he he was teaching diamond way
and people were listening through the
windows and stuff and then he told his
students that's not
really correct you know people who don't
have the lam rim they they shouldn't be
listening to the diamond way teachings
and then they said well the you know
what are you going to do and he said the
best thing is if we had kind of a
separate
[Music]
place to to do those teachings and we
could close the doors and stuff like
that, you know, and then uh and then all
the students are like, "Oh god, he has
another project, you know, and you think
I'm bad." Uh then
uh he said, "Who's going to build a a
tantric monastery
and teaching hall?" And then all the old
students are like, "Oh my god, we
already went through this, you know, and
they just kind of look
away." And then there was there was a
quiet student. Uh and he he's like, "Oh,
none of these none of these great
students is answering the teacher. I
better promise." And he did it. He did
it. He built Gimme Tenture College. My
teacher went there. My teacher was the
assistant abbot of Kumi. And um so
anyway
uh some somebody was offering to to
to create a similar place near my house
uh in case I can't travel much. So, uh
there's a large property near my house
and uh it has a river going through it
and it's quite beautiful and it's a
secret valley and uh so uh
somebody's somebody has an idea to to
prep. There's a building there which
might be nice. So, so if it if I need it
later they they're making that. So, I
don't know. Shopping put it they put an
offer on the land yesterday. Uh, no. It
was
accepted. Sorry, they put it two days
ago. It was accepted yesterday.
Okay. Uh, and uh, the river, which is
very rare in Arizona, by the way. That's
why this land is here, because there's a
river, there's a spring, bare springs.
If you find water in Arizona, you buy
it. Uh, and there's very, very few. And
uh that's why there was a lot of
fighting here uh about the water here.
So anyway,
um the water there in Rimrock, it's a
hidden valley and it goes in a strange
uh it flows in a strange shape and it's
called Dragon Head. Uh the the valley is
called Dragon Head, a secret valley
called Dragon Head. And you can go in
and out of Rimrock and you won't see it.
Uh so anyway uh I don't know why I'm
talking about that. Uh Nagaja is
connected with long with dragon. Okay.
There's something about dragons. Okay.
All right. Uh the second stream comes
down through Arya Asanga. Okay. Next
between Yeah. I like this. I think it's
an old Chinese statue. I I don't know.
Yeah. Stanley. Yeah. And uh you know him
from whose class
yesterday? Yeah, Tim's class. Yeah,
Tim's class was Arya Sa's class. And uh
generally we say that uh the great
teachings on
bodhicitta come down through him. Okay.
So when you study lam rim, you're
getting these two great streams are
coming into your heart. Okay. And this
is uh what's the most bodhicha thing
he's famous for? $100. Rob, wake him
up. See how money circulates here?
People give me red envelope. I give it
away. My wife says, "We have any money
for the cafe?" I'm like,
"No, take that money." Oh. Oh, it's me
again. Nice.
So, so uh master sa went to a retreat uh
for 12 years and he wanted to see uh
Lord Maitraa but uh he was annoyed like
at least three times. He left three
times and he went back. The last time he
went out uh he saw a a female dog and uh
the lower body was eaten by was being
eaten by megas. And so he had this
moment of uh um great compassion and he
carried a dog and uh into his um cave. I
think he um he traded his staff for uh
golden uh what what is called um the
razor. Yeah, razor. and he cut he cut he
cut off a piece of his um flesh and uh
he decided to move the maggots to the
flesh so that both uh both the maggots
and the dog would live. But when he um I
think when he um he saw that if he use
his fingers the magus would die. So he
decided to use his tongue and he closed
his eyes and uh and uh he was reaching
for the maggots but he opened his eyes.
There's no magus. There's no dog.
There's uh Laita. That's his and then
that's why he sold my tria. Yeah.
Yay. Good
story. It's almost a $200 answer, but
nah.
Okay. All right. But it's a great
answer. Okay. Yeah. So, anyway, you when
you think about it in Diamond Way, you
know, he's famous. He's uh he's just as
busy as we are and he has lots of
important things to do and he stops to
help a a dog that got hurt on the road,
you know. And uh I I used to do that
when I was
younger. Every time I saw an animal got
hurt on the road, I'll stop and try to
take care of it. And uh usually you
don't get where you're going.
And you know any I think when you get
older you decide it's not worth the time
but it is worth you know he decided it's
worth the time. So okay
uh next picture you guys
uh this is Lord Atisha. He lived about
almost a thousand years after
uh Arya Nearjuna and Arya Sa. And
uh you know he he helped bring the
teachings uh to to the Himalayas to
Tibet and uh he brought both streams. He
he he designed a a flow of both streams
of of uh nagaraja and aanga. So he
design he designed the lroom rim or he
helped start the alarm tradition and uh
as I mentioned at the stupa the other
day uh he studied in Malaysia and he
studied in Indonesia.
uh and at that time uh those two
countries were
the Buddhism was stronger in Malaysia
and Indonesia than it was in India and
then it was in China. So, so great uh
Chinese monks, great uh Indian monks
used to go to Malaysia or Indonesia to
to study and uh Sugang and Shinten have
a lot of programs at those at those
places where the great where where's it
called? Jambu Jambi Jambi
uh they they have a lot of programs at
that actual place. So, I think it's cool
to study there where Atisha studied. So
Atisha went especially the bodhic sappa
teachings he got them from Malaysia from
Indonesia. He went on a ship very very
dangerous at that time in you know South
China Sea with with lots of
hurricanes and in a small wooden boat
you know so uh he was very very brave. I
I when I think about uh Atisha
uh I think
about traveling to to learn the dharma.
Okay. And uh so when I graduate when I
was in university I I studied overseas.
I got a grant to study
overseas and then uh my plan was to come
back to
Delmare and uh and surf for the rest of
my life. Now I had a place chosen and I
had a surfboard. It was called uh what
was it called? Blue Fire or something.
And uh I had a good surfboard that I
used in Hawaii for a long time. And uh
so I was all set up. I had apartment
chosen. I had the beach chosen, you
know. And then I got interested in L
room. H
uh and then I asked who's the who's the
greatest teacher in the world. I asked
all these high teachers, high high
teachers, and they said uh his name is
Ken Rimpy, you know. And I'm like, where
does he live? And they're like, "You're
so lucky. He's he's in America, you
know." I'm like, "Wow." And I said,
"Where?" And they said, "New Jersey."
And I'm like, "So, if you know about New
Jersey, uh, this is south of New York.
And this is where they make all the
gasoline in the United States. The ships
come in from Arab countries, etc.
They deliver the the raw oil to New
Jersey and then they cook it and they
make gasoline for the whole United
States and then people waste it.
Americans won't walk across the street
to the store. They'll get in their car
and they'll drive across the street to
go to the store. and and so uh that part
of the United States it smells so bad
from the cooking the gasoline it's
there's two names one is cancer alley
and I used to travel through there every
day for 19 years and the other name is
armpit of the
country because it smells so bad. So he
called New Jersey the armpit of America.
And uh then they said New Jersey and I'm
like then I'm like I I don't think I
could go there. I I don't think I could.
When I was a kid in Phoenix and people
drive from New Jersey, black car, nobody
drives a black car in in Arizona except
people from New Jersey. And then uh
they're like these these white white
faces and they're looking out staring at
the they're afraid to get out of their
car and we used to throw uh fruits at
them. Uh we used to throw things at them
cuz we didn't like them, you know. And
and then he's they're like, "You have to
go to New Jersey." I'm like, "No, no,
no, no, no." You know, and then I
thought, "I'll just go for a little
while and uh then I'll go surf. then
I'll continue my surfing uh career, you
know. And uh so I went I went and I got
stuck for 25 years. Okay. And I and
u when I think about my life, that was
the smartest thing I ever did, you know,
like
I went to
uh stay with the teacher and uh I went
where the teaching was. You know what I
mean? even though it was the
armpit and uh and I'm very happy I'm so
happy I did that you know so what I'm
saying is uh these examples of people
like Shenzang or
Atisha they they risk their life to
travel you just get on a plane for two
three hours you know they risk their
life they walk for 17 years
uh to get the teaching so I think if
you're serious about diamond Okay. Uh,
you have to be flexible about where you
live and and what's your occupation and
things like that. If you're going to be
serious, I don't think it's good to be
unemployed. I think that's not good.
My experience many years of teaching
diamond way my experience is uh if you
don't have some work uh which is
honest work and you can make enough
money to support yourself if you're
asking other people for money all the
time and you you can't pay your rent and
you're you're trying
to we always say if a person shows up if
an American shows up sorry who is
studying Diamond Way watch your couch
and bought your refrigerator.
Uh, and that's not good, you know. It
shouldn't be like that. Okay, a diamond
way
person should have a good job. They
should enjoy their work. Uh, it's not
wrong to be a vice president of the
largest jewelry company in the world and
be diamond weight person. That's okay.
If you can't handle those two together,
you're not practicing diamond way. Okay?
Uh it's
a it is diamond way. Diamond way means
you can sit in a corporate office and be
practicing all day long. Okay? It
doesn't mean you give up your job and
and go sit at Diamond Mountain. Okay?
But
uh you should be willing and able to
travel to where you need to to uh to
study Diamond Way. Okay. With the money
that you made in your good job. Okay.
got it and you support your family and
you don't you don't you don't keep
asking other people for money or help.
You should you should stand on your own.
Okay? You shouldn't your your religious
practice shouldn't bother other people.
That's kind of contradiction, you know.
Oh, I I'm I'm diamond way. I don't have
to work. Can you loan me $200? You know,
and they're like, if you're diamond way,
why don't you go make some money?
So you should have a good job, you know,
and and I
think having a good job is a a good
place to practice diamond way. I think
so. Have running a company or or
something like that. Uh it's a wonderful
place to practice diamond way. Okay.
There were people in my
company who didn't know I was a monk
for for 15 years. They didn't know I was
a Buddhist, you know. I just quietly do
my thing. I just do my work. Nobody
knew. Finally, they found
out. And I had a lot of Chinese uh
employees because we had a refugee
program for Chinese from
Cambodia. And we hired a lot of
refugees. uh Vietnam. Uh and uh so
we finally they all these Asian people
found out I was a Buddhist, you know.
And I'm like, you know, and then they
said, "Can we meet your teacher?" And
I'm like,
"No." And they said, "Why?" And I said,
"Cuz he doesn't like me and he will tell
you bad things about me." And they're
like, "Insist, insist." You know,
because he always criticized me all the
time. He called me all kinds of bad
names. Bangu or pungu. Say bangu. Pongu.
Different, right? Bangu.
Pongu. Bangu means
horsefly. Fly, you know. Uh, and then
pongu means
jackass. And uh if he's in a good mood,
he call me bangu. If he's in a bad mood,
he call me bungu, you know. I said, you
don't want to meet my teacher. He he he
just tell you I'm a bangu or a bongo,
you know. And they're like, come on,
please let us meet your teacher, you
know. So
finally, you know, they came down and
and like 10 Chinese people and
Vietnamese and uh I said, "Okay, go go
go ahead." and he came down and and I
used to translate for him.
Yeah. I used to translate his English
into
English and uh so so I would always sit
with him when he was meeting people and
uh we went up and then he said, "Mike,
you can leave." You know, Pungu, you can
leave. You know, and I'm like, "No, I
got a translate for you." And he's like,
"No, you can leave." And then he left. I
left. And then they spent a long time,
like an hour. And uh then they all came
down and they're like, "Oh, Ghi
Michael, you know, you are so great, so
holy, you know, and I'm like, what did
he say?"
And then uh I don't
know the point of it is uh for diamond
way uh you don't have a place. Your
place is where your teacher is. Okay. If
it's possible, you know, uh you don't
have a So I stayed in New Jersey for 25
years. Finally, I escaped to
Arizona. Okay. All right. What I'm
saying is
uh you
know the most important thing is to
learn and to go where you can learn.
Okay? And I'm preaching to the choir.
That's a new idiom
standing in the church. The people who
come every Sunday, the only people who
come every Sunday is the singers, the
choir. Then every Sunday the priest has
to give a talk. Then the only people in
the whole town who learn all of the
priest talk is the choir because they
have to be there to do the music. So we
call preaching to the choir. It means uh
you guys traveled
here to uh learn diamond way. So you
don't need to hear this talk. You're
already here. So anyway, I'm just
preaching to the choir. All right.
Um, by the way, uh, Sagei Aral, uh, the
VP of, uh, DCI and
SEIM, he's not I don't know if he's here
this morning, but he he,
uh, he translated a book, uh, based on
Lord Atisha's teachings, and it is
amazing. It is incredible. Uh, you know,
so if
you Is it out yet? I don't think Not
yet. Well, we're we're just about to put
it out, but it's a Lojong book. It's a
based on the Lojong. It's called
the Crown of Nas or something like that.
And it's a very very powerful book. And
in there, there's a history of where
those teachings come from. Uh and it
took a many it took many years. It took
us about eight years to finish the book.
Okay. And we used
uh we wrote a very beautiful history of
the L rim. If you're in staircase house,
you should get that book. Okay? And we
wrote we put together a nice history of
the L rim and the Lojo teachings. And uh
we
used uh John Brady's work from Mongolia.
So he's he has a team in Mongolia for 17
years and they are saving the books
there. There's 300,000 I estimate
300,000 books there, different books and
uh he's been working on that. So we used
his his work. So we should give John a
hand.
[Applause]
By the way, John, Connie, Ally, other
people are teach they are continuing the
retreat here and they're teaching
Diamond Way the whole 18 courses. And if
you have any time or any chance, uh you
should learn from them also. It's very
very it's very very cool and they're
doing a good job all over the world.
They're teaching people all over the
world.
Keep
[Applause]
your Yeah. Okay.
Uh, next
picture. Um, if we're talking about the
lineage, which is very important, you
know, who passed on these teachings?
uh and I received uh lam rim together
with diamond way. So I got them from the
same teacher. Uh that's the teacher on
the right side
uh Ken rib gi loan. And
um so I I lived with him for 25 years
and uh he taught us lam rim. He taught
lam every day
for 25 years. And then he taught diamond
way for uh over 20 years. And uh we had
to memorize the
book. We had to memorize it. Not like
you guys. It's a it's a it's like an
hour and a half.
and
uh and he he as I mentioned I mean he
was a very high ge he uh was in a debate
with 15,000 monks and he was he was
number one he beat he beat the other
15,000 monks then the the government of
Tibet gave him you know what's the
highest prize in
Tibet it's one brick of Chinese tea
uh and um a sheep's stomach full of
butter cuz they don't have
plastic. Uh and it's the only way to
carry food. It's the only way to keep
food from spoiling. So they take the
stomach out of a sheep and they store
the butter in the stomach. It's kind of
gross, but uh but that's the award. If
you beat 15,000 monks, you get tea and
butter. Uh so anyway, he's
extraordinary scholar.
And then uh he became uh he finished his
gish in in
in the gish tradition. You cannot study
diamond way until you finish gish. Only
a gish can go to the diamond way
college. So uh the only only a gish can
study diamond way. You can get an
initiation from your
teacher and and you can learn you can
learn basic diamond way from your
teacher but if you don't finish a gishi
course you can't go to the secret
monasteries. Uh so he finished number
one. Uh I'm a ling gish. Ling gash means
uh kind of local gish in my
monastery. So I studied 25 years. I got
ling gish but uh haram he's haram.
means after you finish ling you study
for like another 12 years over 30 years
and you debate all the monks in all the
monasteries and and then you get a super
gish degree. So he got that degree and
then he went uh to tantric college and
he studied there and uh he studied it
very very well and then he taught it to
to us he taught it to I don't know how
many jigme 30 people I don't
know maybe 30 who taught vajioini I
don't know maybe 30 people but uh for
for for like 20 years it's Okay. Um, he
was taught by Tjang Rimpache, but you
should know your lineage. Okay. You
should know your Now you're part of I I
know you're all separate houses, but
you're you're all part of diamond house
in a way. you graduate from the four
houses to the diamond house and or you
live in both two houses but um so anyway
uh he was taught diamond way by tanguche
uh who's in the middle and u he was the
teacher of the current diamama he in
Tibet when the dalama is a kid
uh they choose the two greatest gishes
in the country uh they're called senior
tutor and junior tutor. So he was the
tutor for the da. He raised him
philosophically. He taught him
philosophically for many many years 20
25 years. And uh he was my teacher's
teacher. So so you're of the same uh
that's
your that's your
great-grandfather. So Kenj is your
grandfather. I'm not always your yay.
Then uh Cha Rimpich is his teacher. Then
you should know who Chaiche's teacher is
called Pabongo Rimpache. And uh he's on
the left
side and uh he wrote the liberation in
the palm of your hands which is the
greatest lam rim of all of all the lum
rims. There's many lum rims. He taught
he he he wrote the greatest one and that
we studied for 12 years and my teacher
taught it to me for almost 30 years.
Okay. And uh so you studied it for 12
years.
Pabongok so obviously he's a great uh
lam teacher but also uh he is the main
holder of diamond way in Tibet at that
time. Okay. He's the main. Uh, you
okay? You
okay? Let's catch him. Let's catch
him. We got a spider. No, she didn't get
[Music]
bitten. Let's do
that. Yeah, we'll take a 15-minute break
now. We'll find a creature who
interrupted at the most important
moment, which I'm sure it's just a
coincidence.
And I'll see you in 15 minutes. Okay. 88